Guide to the George Carter Collection of AIDS Research MSS.560
Fales Library and Special Collections
George Carter Collection of AIDS Research
1984-2015
Fales Library and Special Collections
Carter, George
MSS.560
34 Linear Feet in 32 record cartons and 4 manuscript boxes
1.68 Gigabytes in 9 computer files
George Carter is an activist and researcher of HIV and AIDS prevention and treatments. Carter joined ACT UP/New York in 1989 and as part of the Treatment and Data Committee helped release the "AIDS Chart" which provided information on the latest drugs and information available to fight AIDS and related infections, including information on alternative and complementary treatments. Carter served as the director for DAAIR (Direct Access Alternative Information Resources), a not-for-profit buyers club for alternative treatments. He founded the Foundation for Integrative AIDS Research (FIAR), a not-for-profit organization that focuses on prevention and treatment of HIV, AIDS, and chronic hepatitis and supports clinical trials of herbal and nutritional treatments. The materials in this collection include research articles on opportunistic infections and alternative treatments from FIAR, ACT UP administrative and program files, and various drafts of Carter's research and writings.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
George Carter is an activist and writer who researches HIV and AIDS treatment and prevention, with a focus on alternative treatments. Carter joined ACT UP/New York in 1989 and as part of the Treatment and Data Committee, and wrote and distributed extensive charts detailing the latest drugs and information available to fight AIDS and related opportunistic infections. These tables included information on pharmaceutical drugs as well as alternative and complementary treatments.
Carter was the director for the Treatment Information Development for DAAIR (Direct Access Alternative Information Resources), a not-for-profit buyers' club for alternative treatments. He also started the Foundation for Integrative AIDS Research (FIAR) in conjunction with Columbia University to pursue clinical studies where drug treatment is not readily available.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by George Carter, 2018. The accession number associated with this gift is 2018.115.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of materials collected and written by George Carter, an activist who researches HIV and AIDS preventions and treatments. Materials in this collection date from 1984-2015 and include administrative files from his times working with ACT UP, DAAIR (Direct Access Alternative Information Resources), and FIAR (Foundation for Integrative AIDS Research). Included are his own writings in the form of articles, pamphlets, conference papers, and activist and research related correspondence. Of significance are drafts of the "AIDS Chart" which he began to write and distribute in 1991 during his time at ACT UP/New York, which explained the latest drugs and information available to fight AIDS and related opportunistic infections, including information on alternative and complementary treatments.
Additionally the collection includes research files on opportunistic infections and HIV/AIDS treatment and preventions from the Foundation for Integrative AIDS Research (FIAR), a not-for-profit organization started by Carter which is dedicated to researching issues relevant to the prevention and treatment of HIV and chronic hepatitis, and supporting clinical trials of herbal and nutritional treatments.
The collection also includes a digital copy of the documentary, I Am Not What You See, which focuses on South East Asian individuals who identify as having a third gender.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
HIV infections; AIDS (Disease) -- New York (State) -- New York.; AIDS activists.; AIDS activists -- New York (N.Y.); AIDS (Disease); Opportunistic infections; Alternative medicine.; ACT UP (Organization); Foundation for Integrative Aids Research
- Opportunitic Infections: Articles, 1991-2010 (Box 1)
- Pathogenesis: Articles, Notes, 1993-2010 (Box 2)
- Micronutrients: Articles, 1986-2008 (Box 3)
- Botanical Treatments/Systems of Medicine: Articles, Correspondence, 1990-2008 (Box 4)
- Side effects: Articles, Correspondence, 1998-2010 (Box 5)
- Government (CDC, FDA, etc): Articles, Correspondence, 1993-2010 (Box 6)
- Amino acids, Glutathione, NAC: Articles, Correspondence, 1983-2010 (Box 7)
- Oxidative Stress: Articles, Drafts, 1996-2007 (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous Alternative Treatments: Articles, 1993-2010 (Box 9)
- Hep/NeuroHepatitis C: Articles, Newsletters, 1998-2009 (Box 10)
- Antivirals, Novel: Articles, Correspondence, Notes, Newsletters, 1991-2009 (Box 11)
- DAAIR, NYBC: Correspondence, Drafts, Notes, 1991-2015 (Box 12)
- FIAR/Projects, Mount Sinai: Articles, Correspondence, 1993-2010 (Box 13)
- Misc. Presentations: Correspondence, Drafts, Newsletters, Notes, 1992-2011 (Box 14)
- FIAR/Sinai - Projects: Articles, Correspondence, Notes, 1990-2015 (Box 15)
- Pharma and Politix: Articles, Notes, 1999-2009 (Box 16)
- FIAR-Projects 2: Articles, Correspondence, 1996-2014 (Box 17)
- Older Conferences/Presentations: Articles, Correspondence, Drafts, 1993-1995 (Box 18)
- FIAR Projects 3: Articles, Correspondence, 1996-2012 (Box 19)
- Miscellaneous: Denialist articles, DAAIR, Treatment and Data Committee agendas, 1991-2009 (Box 20)
- Articles, Serials, ACT UP reports, 1988-1994 (Box 21)
- Articles, Serials, 1991-1993 (Box 22)
- ACT UP administrative material, 1990-1994 (Box 23)
- ACT UP, 1992-1995 (Box 24)
- Articles, Correspondence, Serials, 1990-1995 (Box 25)
- ACT UP Press, 1992-1993 (Box 26)
- ACT UP Correspondence, Reports, Press, 1984-1996
  - Paper Materials (Box 27)
  - Digital Materials, FA_MSS_560_ER_1
- ACT UP, 1990-1992 (Box 28)
- Journals, Newsletters, 1996-2006 (Box 29)
- Journals, Newsletters, 1996-2006 (Box 30)
- AIDS Chart Drafts, ACT UP Memorandum, Corerspondence, Notes, 1991-1999 (Box 31)
- Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 32)
- Newsletters, Reports, 1992-2006 (Box 33)
- Correspondence, Newsletters, Press, 1991-1999 (Box 34)
- ACT UP Memorandum, Reports, Media; Articles, 1992-1998 (Box 35)
- ACT UP Notes, Articles, 1993-1999 (Box 36)
- I Am Not What You See, FA_MSS_560_ER_2